[Music]
welcome to this session about mocking
outbound calls for easier testing I'm
Stefan and with me I have balash and
we're going to talk about what's new in
this
release when we build applications that
rely on external Services we are often
challenged with testing the integration
code itself if we connect to the actual
service we need to consider how that
service will be impacted by running
tests will it impact production perhaps
is there rate limits is there other
scenarios we need to think about if we
actually hit the end point during our
test runs and how can we make sure that
tests are isolated when we run them
repeatedly and how can we make sure that
we maintain a consistent behavior on the
external endpoint between test runs if
we then take in the external service and
try to simulate it in our test
environment but outside
BC we are challenged with other
scenarios like changing the versions and
changing the behavior and making sure
things are aligned between the test code
and the the actual service that we are
testing in our test
environment even if we isolate the
request to the external services and
test the consumption of the results or
the data that produced for the service
there might still be scenarios where we
cannot do that where there's a
dependency that talks to an external
service and we still want to handle that
to address many of these challenges we
have introduced a new test Handler in
this release the HTTP client Handler and
to teach us about how to use this test
Handler I have Bales to help us know and
understand how to use this feature thank
you Stefan well in this demo I'm going
to walk you through how you can set up
an HTTP client Handler to test your
outbound HTTP requests in your Al test
as an example let's take a look at the
document service it has two methods to
get document content and the delete
document and both make an HTTP request
to an external service to verify that
the get document content works as
expected we can create a test code unit
and write a simple test method like so
however this setup requires that the
external service is up and running
instead we can define an HTTP client
hander to intercept the request and
simulate a response for it
we can start by defining a procedure and
adding the HTTP client Handler attribute
to it within the Handler we can simulate
the response to a request by populating
the properties of the response
object finally we can attach the Handler
to the test method using the Handler
functions attribute when the test is run
the HTTP request will be intercepted and
routed to the Handler which will mock
the response for the best coverage we
might want to test that our code can
handle all kinds of different cases not
only successful ones for
example error responses that we can
simulate by setting the status code and
the reason phrase
accordingly unsuccessful requests for
example due to a timeout a DNS
resolution or some kind of network
connectivity issue and requests that got
blocked by the environment keep in mind
that when an HTTP client Handler is
attached to a test method then all HTTP
calls that occur during the execution of
the test will be routed to the hander
for processing therefore if you were to
for example invoke the delete document
in the same test method then both the
get and the delete request would need to
be handled by the same hander procedure
to know which request is being processed
we can analyze the properties of the
request
object we can distinguish between the
two by only looking at the request type
property in this case when the request
is of type delete we send the 501 not
implemented response while for the get
request we send the 200 success response
great but what if we are expecting
multiple different requests with the
same request type then we can use the
path and query parameters of the request
to know how to populate the
response it is important to mention that
as of now it is not possible to set
cookies or redirection status
codes so far so good we can
differentiate between requests and
simulate the response
accordingly however as some of you may
know it is possible to set the request
URI by using a secret text in that case
neither the path nor the query
parameters are available as the request
URI must not be exposed in that case we
can use the has secret URI property of
the request to filter for this
case but then naturally comes the
question is there an other way to handle
this scenario other than throwing an
exception what if let's say the request
is coming from a dependency that we do
not want to Mark in general is there a
way to only mock certain requests while
letting others make it to the external
endpoint the answer is yes we have
implemented a fall through mechanism
that allows the programmer to decide in
the Handler whether they want to Mark
the response for a request or issue the
original
one like so
in this case when the request has a
secret URI then we just decide to issue
the original request as well as when the
path is pointing to the SL pictures
endpoint when the request is pointing to
the/ documents endpoint we mock the
response this can be achieved via the
Boolean return value of the hander
procedure we can use an exit true
statement if we want to issue the
original request conversely we can use
an exit ex it false statement if you
want to mock response to be used keep in
mind that the default return value is
false therefore a completely empty
hander procedure would still block the
outbound request and return a mocked
response now let's put it all together
into one big procedure that is able to
handle most of the previously defined
cases just for fun let's see how the
marking goes in action in a debug
session
let's publish the app and start a debu
session then we can load and run the
document service
tests the get document content test is
run first it invokes the get document
content method with the dummy document
ID which makes a get request to the
Local Host / documents
endpoint the request is then intercepted
by the Handler we can look at the
properties of the request object and
confirm that it is indeed the get
request coming from the get document
content then the Handler extracts the
document ID from the query parameters
and fabricates an example
content finally it populates the status
code and reason phrase to simulate a
successful request and uses an exit fall
statement to make sure that the mock
response is used stepping back into the
get document content method we can
analyze the response subject and confirm
that it contains the marked values
including the content that needs to be
extracted first the content check passes
and the test successfully
completes the delete document test is
run afterwards it invokes the delete
document method with a dummy document ID
which makes a delete request to the
Local Host / doents
endpoint the request is intercepted by
the Handler and we can verify the
request by looking at the properties
just like before
as the request is of type delete the
Handler simulates a 501 not implemented
response and returns with an exit false
statement as the response object
received by the delete document method
does not have a success status code it
signals an unsuccessful delete operation
by returning false therefore the test
fails with a document deletion failed
error finally I'd like to draw your
attention to this new property that we
have introduced called test http request
policy you can add it to test code units
to specify how outbound request should
be treated during test executions by
default all requests are allowed but you
can further restrict this to only allow
ones issued from a Handler or to block
all unhandled requests the following
tabl shows an overview of all of the
scenarios we can see the different
hander setups on the left while the
property values at the top and the
outcome for all of these scenarios in
the
middle let's take a look at all of them
in a bit more detail when the property
is set to allow all outbound requests
which is also the default value then no
restrictions are imposed on outbound
requests to illustrate the three main
scenarios we can take a look at the
example on the right it has three test
methods one with no Handler one with a
Handler that issues the original request
using an exit true statement and one
with a Handler that mock a response in
this case all three are allowed when the
property is set to allow outbound from
Handler then only those outbound
requests are allowed that are first
intercepted by an HTTP client Handler
and then issued to the external endpoint
by a Handler for through using an exit
true
statement this is to ensure that no
unintentional requests are made if you
look at the same test setup we can see
that the first test that has no Handler
it's blocked as it tries to make a call
directly to the external endpoint while
the one where the Handler issues the
original request is allowed when the
property is set to block outbound
requests then all outbound requests must
be intercepted and handled by an HTTP
client Handler this can be very useful
if you don't want frequent test
executions in your automated cicd
pipelines to hit the actual endpoint in
the example we can see that the first
two methods that try to make a call to
the external endpoint are blocked and
only the one that simulates a response
is
allowed that's been it from me thank you
very much for your attention